Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is nun
daled נד. nun daled. We're just back, so we start on nun
gimmel amud beis נג עמוד ב. nun gimmel amud beis. And we
were talking about the way the Kohen Gadol כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
would walk backwards out of the Kodesh Kodashim קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim,
and then we translated that to walking backwards when one departs from
his rebbi רבי, rebbi, so sort of the transference of that sense
of the center from being the Mikdash מקדש Mikdash to Torah תורה
Torah and the representative of Torah תורה, Torah, and then to more
of a direct God encounter, the stepping back when one finishes shmoneh
esrei שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei.
So now we are on nun gimmel amud beis נג עמוד ב
nun gimmel amud beis
where the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this. Tanya nami hachi תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, the line second line from the middle
sized lines, very beginning. Hamispalel tzarich sheyafsiya shalosh pesiot leachora המתפלל צריך
שיפסיע שלוש פסיעות לאחוריו, Hamispalel tzarich sheyafsiya shalosh pesiot leachora,
the one who prays has to step three steps behind himself, three
steps backwards. Veachar kach yiten shalom ואחר כך יתן שלום, Veachar kach
yiten shalom, and then say oseh shalom עושה שלום. oseh shalom. Veim
lo asa ken ואם לא עשה כן, Veim lo asa ken, and
if he did not do this, ra'uy shelo hitpalel ראוי שלא התפלל,
ra'uy shelo hitpalel, it's better not to have prayed because I guess
the way you end the prayer sort of affects the entire nature
of the prayer, and therefore the whole thing is worthless, which is
a pretty harsh statement. Rashi
רש"י Rashi says ra'uy shelo hitpalel ראוי שלא התפלל, ra'uy shelo hitpalel,
ra'uy hayo lo im lo hitpalel kemit'to ראוי היה לו אם לא
התפלל כמותו. ra'uy hayo lo im lo hitpalel kemit'to. No, okay, he
doesn't add anything. It would have been better not to have prayed.
Umishum Shmaya amru ומשום שמעיה אמרו, Umishum Shmaya amru, in the name
of Shmaya they said, shenoten shalom liyamin veachar kach lismol שנותן שלום
לימין ואחר כך לשמאל. shenoten shalom liyamin veachar kach lismol. First you
say oseh shalom bimromav עושה שלום במרומיו. oseh shalom bimromav. First you
give peace to the right and then you do it to the
left. Now, if anybody knows, we do it the opposite, and we'll
get to that in a minute. Shene'emar mimino esh das lamo שנאמר
מימינו אש דת למו, Shene'emar mimino esh das lamo, from God's right
hand is the law of fire to him to the people, so
God you first focus on the
right. Veomer yipol mitzidcha elef urevava miminecha ואומר יפול מצדך אלף ורבבה
מימינך, Veomer yipol mitzidcha elef urevava miminecha, a thousand shall fall by
your side and a myriad by your right. So myriad is ten
thousand, much more than a thousand, so again the general preference of
halacha הלכה halacha to the right. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says
we're not done. Mai veomer מאי ואומר, Mai veomer, what's the extra
pasuk adding? Vechi teima orcha demilsa hi lemisav yamin וכי תימא אורחא
דמילתא היא למיסב ימין, Vechi teima orcha demilsa hi lemisav yamin, sure
God gives the Torah in the right hand because you normally do
things with your right hand since most of the world is righties.
I'm talking here as a lefty, actually everybody in my family,
my wife, my kids, they're all lefties anyway. Tashma תא שמע Tashma
yipol mitzidcha elef urevava miminecha יפול מצדך אלף ורבבה מימינך. yipol mitzidcha
elef urevava miminecha. So you see it's not just about the act
of giving something, in general there's a favoring of the right hand.
So that would seem that you first say oseh shalom bimromav עושה
שלום במרומיו, oseh shalom bimromav, you bow to your right. Okay, but
we're not done. Rava רבא Rava chazyei חזיה chazyei leAbaye לאביי, leAbaye,
Rava saw Abaye, dehu yav shalom liyaminah beraysha
דהוא יהב שלום לימינה ברישא. dehu yav shalom liyaminah beraysha. First he
said that he did this, first he said oseh shalom bimromav עושה
שלום במרומיו oseh shalom bimromav to his right. Amar lei אמר ליה,
Amar lei, and now he corrected him. Mi savart liyamin didach מי
סברת לימין דידך? Mi savart liyamin didach? No, no, no, you got
it wrong. We don't mean first you give peace to your right
side. Lismol didach dehu yemino shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu לשמאל דידך דהוא
ימינו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. Lismol didach dehu yemino shel Hakadosh Baruch
Hu. First you bow to your left side, why? Because you're leaving
God, so giving shalom to the right means to the right as
if God were in your presence, which means to your left, to
God's right, and that is what we do. Amar Chiya brei deRav
Huna אמר חייא בריה דרב הונא, Amar Chiya brei deRav Huna, chazinalei
חזינא ליה chazinalei leAbaye veRava לאביי ורבא, leAbaye veRava, they did the
three backwards with one bow. Dipsilu shalosh pesiot bechriyah achas דפסיעו שלוש
פסיעות בכריעה אחת. Dipsilu shalosh pesiot bechriyah achas. They did the three
backwards with one prostration, presumably they were bowed down as they did
the three steps backwards, so as not just another way of taking
leave is bowing down. And we mentioned that also yesterday about Rabbi
Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who would prostrate himself on the ground
until Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had departed. Okay, so that
is walking backwards, and again an interesting intersection of Mikdash מקדש Mikdash
and Tefilla תפילה. Tefilla. And from that we transition to the next
intersection of Mikdash מקדש Mikdash and Tefilla תפילה, Tefilla, when the Kohen
Gadol כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would leave, and after he left the
Kodesh Kodashim קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, he would make a small prayer
in the Heichal היכל Heichal before exiting the Heichal היכל. Heichal. Umitpalel
tefilla ketzara bevayis hachitzon ומתפלל תפילה קצרה בבית החיצון, Umitpalel tefilla ketzara
bevayis hachitzon, that's now going back to the Mishna משנה. Mishna. So
mai mitzlei מאי מצלי, mai mitzlei, what would he pray? Rava bar
Rav Adda veRavin bar Rav Adda רבא בר רב אדא ורבין בר
רב אדא, Rava bar Rav Adda veRavin bar Rav Adda, tuvayei mishmei
deRav amri תרווייהו משמיה דרב אמרי. tuvayei mishmei deRav amri. So both
of these say in the name of Rav. So here's what he
would say. Yehi ratzon milifanecha Hashem Elokeinu shetehei shana zo geshuma ushchuna
יהי רצון מלפניך השם אלקינו שתהא שנה זו גשומה ושחונה. Yehi ratzon
milifanecha Hashem Elokeinu shetehei shana zo geshuma ushchuna. May it be Thy
will that this year shall be
rainy and hot. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says shchuna שחונה? shchuna?
Maliusa hi מעליותא היא? Maliusa hi? What, is an overly hot year
a good thing? I mean the emphasis of shchuna שחונה shchuna means
more hot than normal. Ella eima אלא אימא, Ella eima, no, here's
what he would say. Im shchuna tehei geshuma אם שחונה תהא גשומה.
Im shchuna tehei geshuma. If it's going to be too hot, let
it at least also be rainy to offset the heat. And this
was a primary concern of course about the crops, not about their
own comfort. Rav Acha רב אחא, Rav Acha, if anybody remembers the
liturgy of Yom Kippur יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, after we do the
whole avoda עבודה, avoda, right, we have the that the Kohen Gadol
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would say a prayer. I would say it's
a prayer, and we have not a very short prayer, we have
a quite long one, right, I think it's with the אלף בית
Alef Bais and the whole thing. Somewhere in there is גשומה
עם שחונה, Geshuma Im Shchuna, right, let it be rainy if it's
going to be hot, but it's a quite, you know, whole blown
paragraph prayer, not a, not a short one like this.
Right, ולא יהא, Velo Yehe, ואף
על פי ששלון היה אומר יהי רצון שלא תהא בתיהם קבריהם, Af
Al Pi She-Shalon Haya Omer Yehi Ratzon She-Lo Tehe Bateihem Kivreihem, right.
So anyway, but what's interesting is that of all the things to
single out, it was this issue, which just goes to show the
reality of being in an agricultural society, like of let, you know,
the one thing you're going to say is this one thing. So
it's about the concern that the weather would be, you know, appropriate,
it would be as is needed. So, the Gemara says רב אחא
בריה דרבא מסיים בה משמיה דרב יהודה, Rav Acha Brei DeRava Mesayem
Ba Mishme DeRav Yehuda, so that, so he felt that wasn't enough
just to pray for the weather. So he had the following conclusion.
Now, it doesn't mean that's just what he, he would have said
if he was a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, is he reporting what
he believes the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol actually did say? Anyway, but
here's how he, he ended it. So, לא יעדי Lo Ya'adi and
it's interesting also now the shift from Hebrew to Aramaic. לא יעדי
עבידי שולטנא מבית יהודה, Lo Ya'adi Avidi Shultana MiBei Yehuda,
shall not be removed those that embody
dominion from, from the house of Yehuda, meaning let us, you know,
the idea that the kings come from Yehuda, and the belief that
what's his name that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi was a
direct descendant of דוד המלך, David HaMelech, which is, meant that even
in the בית שני, Bayis Sheini, even though they were under foreign
dominion, they still had a degree of their own political control. And
the fact that Rebbe was from, you know, the house of Yehuda,
the house of David gave them that sense of that they still
are, you know, some degree of autonomy and of self-dominion. So here
that would be one of the prayers that we should retain that
as a nation. So it's actually quite powerful if you think about
it because for us, like okay, the one thing you would want
to say is I don't know, let it be good in terms
of health and פרנסה, parnassa, you know, but thinking here at a
national level, right, because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is now representing
the nation at a national level. So first of all, weather applies
to everyone and it's sort of the economic well-being of the people,
but also the sense of a certain degree of autonomy and of
still maintaining, you know, some sense of self-dominion, not really because you're
under foreign rule, but nevertheless. So let the rule, let dominion not
be removed from the house of Yehuda, ולא יהיו עמך ישראל צריכים
לפרנס זה מזה. Velo Yihiyu Amcha Yisrael Tzrichim LeParnas Ze Mi-ze. Let
not your people Israel need to support one another. Again, this is
again just making it broader than just the weather issue, but about
the issue about פרנסה. parnassa. So לפרנס זה מזה leparnas ze mi-ze
means,
you know, if everybody, you know, the מהרש"א Maharsha sort of refers
to a Gemara, a famous Gemara in ברכות, Berachos, where David's advisors
come to him and say, you know, there's, you know, everybody is
poor. So he says, well, let's just let them do business with
one another. So, you know, so it says, ah, that won't work,
if everybody is poor, there's no money coming in. So what you
want is you want a, I'm sure there's an economic term for
this, but what
is it? A positive balance of
payment. Okay, there you go, positive balance of payment. Anyway, so let
the, let us not all be just moving money from one pocket
into the other, let there be actually incoming, incoming money, and let
us, meaning let it be a good year economically for everyone, ולא
תכנס לפניך תפלת עוברי דרכים. Velo Tikanes Lefanecha Tefilas Ovrei Drachim.
And this is getting back to the weather specific issue. Let not
enter in your presence, do not listen to the prayer of עוברי
דרכים, ovrei drachim, those that are going on the roads, because those
that are going on the roads don't want it to be rainy.
So their own, you know, little self-interested personal concerns are certainly not
more important than the national concerns about the proper weather which often
involves a good amount of rain. Okay, so where were we? רבי
חנינא בן דוסא הוה קא אזיל באורחא. Rebbi Chanina Ben Dosa Hava
Ka Azil Be-Orcha. Now we're going to talk about a prayer of
עוברי דרכים. ovrei drachim. רבי חנינא בן דוסא Rebbi Chanina Ben Dosa
was going on the way. שדא מטרא עלוהי, Shada Mitra Allei, so
rain started pouring down on him. אמר, Amar, he said, רבונו של
עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the World, of the universe, כל
עולם כולו בנחת וחנינא בצער? Kol Olam Kulo Be-Nachas Ve-Chanina Be-Tza'ar? Everybody
has it so wonderful, everybody's home, I still here in the middle,
you know, I have 10 miles left to go, I'm in pain?
פסק מטרא. Pasak Mitra. So the rain stopped. כי אתא לביתיה, Ki
Ata Le-Beisei, then he got home, אמר, Amar, he said, רבונו של
עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, כל עולם כולו בצער, Kol Olam Kulo Be-Tza'ar,
everybody now is in anguish because thanks to me you stopped the
rain, וחנינא בנחת, Ve-Chanina Be-Nachas, I should have it easy? What about
all the farmers? So אתא מטרא, Ata Mitra, so then it started
to rain. Okay, I'm not sure what we're supposed to learn from
that other than it's like a type of a, you know, we
do have some of these miracle stories about certain אמוראים Amoraim or
certain תנאים Tannaim that they could, God would automatically listen to everything
they would say. So I suppose if God's going to equally listen
to you to start it again when you get home, you can
pray to him to stop it while you're still on the way.
Okay. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said, מה אהני ליה צלותיה דכהן גדול לגבי רבי חנינא בן דוסא?
Mai Ahani Lei Tzelutei De-Kohen Gadol Legabei Rebbi Chanina Ben Dosa? What
good would the prayer of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol do with
רבי חנינא בן דוסא Rebbi Chanina Ben Dosa in the world? רבי
חנינא בן דוסא, Rebbi Chanina Ben Dosa, God is always going to
listen to him. All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מאי... Mai... one
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol אחד echad שהאריך בתפלתו, she-herich bitfilato, he took
a long time in his prayers, שהאריך בתפלתו, she-herich bitfilato,
now I lost my place, ונמנו אחד הכהנים ve-nimnu echad ha-kohanim להכנס,
le-hikkanes, and they took a vote and they decided even though it
says that nobody can go in, בזו, be-zo, you know, בזאת, be-zot,
you know,
but nevertheless he hasn't come out yet, maybe he's dead, we gotta
send somebody in להכנס אחריו. le-hikkanes acharav. התחילו הם נכנסים, hitchilu hem
nichnasim, they were about to enter in, והוא יוצא, ve-hu yotze, and
he walked out just as they were about to enter in. אמרו
לו, amru lo, they said to him, מפני מה הארכת בתפלתך, mipnei
mah herachta bitfilat-cha, why did you take so long to pray? אמר
להם, amar lahem, he said to them, קשה בעיניכם שנתפללתי עליכם ועל
בית המקדש שלא
יחרב? Kashe be-eineichem she-hitpalalti aleichem ve-al Beit Ha-Mikdash she-lo ye-charev? What, you've
got a complaint against me that I prayed for the well-being of
you, of the people, and of the well-being, interesting theme we had
not seen yet, about the well-being of the המקדש? Mikdash? Because it's
always, it's interesting to think like at what stage of the המקדש
Mikdash were they concerned. You know, in the בית ראשון, Bayis Rishon,
it's quite clear that like a hundred years leading up to the
destruction or more, they knew that the, you know, that the end
was in sight. But in the בית שני, Bayis Sheni, you know,
at what stage did they start feeling like that they were under
threat of it being destroyed? So one again wonders if it's not
the rabbis projecting backwards and imagining that you know, even at the
time of the בית שני, Bayis Sheni, they were praying that it
not be destroyed.
Yeah, I don't have the exact date. So anyway, that's what, so
is it a, is it a problem for you that I prayed
for you and I prayed for the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash that
it shouldn't be destroyed? אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him,
אל תרגיל לעשות כן, al targil la'asot ken, you know what? Thanks
a lot, but do not get into the practice of doing this.
שהרי שנינו לא היה מאריך בתפלתו כדי שלא להבעית את ישראל. she-harei
shaninu lo hayah ma'arich bitfilato kedei she-lo le-hav'it et Yisrael. We have
a משנה, Mishnah, again talking about a little anachronistic, right? So the
משנה Mishnah says you're not supposed to do long דאווענען. davening. You
know again, obviously there were rabbinic teachings still at the time of
the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, you know early משניות, Mishnayos, but שהרי
שנינו she-harei shaninu obviously seems to suggest already the literary corpus of
the משנה Mishnah which they were quoting to him. So it's a
little anachronistic, but you get the point. Don't be such a צדיק,
tzaddik, not even just for yourself, a צדיק tzaddik for other people,
if that's not appropriate in this setting and you're gonna get everybody
worried. Yes.
Have you ever heard this mean me somewhere in the גמרא Gemara
or even sort of like a lore but you know they put
a rope around
the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? Yeah yeah yeah, well that's certainly, that's
certainly not in this story.
I don't know where that's from but not in this story. I've
heard that too? Yeah I have heard that. You happen to know
if it's in the זהר?
Zohar? It's in the זהר, Zohar, the rope idea? Okay. All right.
Next משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara wasn't told about the זהר. Zohar. If the
גמרא Gemara only had ArtScroll would have been so much better.
Okay, there's no question about the next step. All right. I will
let, I will let the ArtScroll figure that out. משניטלו הארון, mishenitlo
ha-Aron, now that we again
we told the story that putting the incense in front of the
ארון, Aron, but the גמרא Gemara pointed out that that was also
anachronistic because it conflated the reality of the two curtains with the
בית שני Bayis Sheni to the reality of the ארון Aron in
the בית ראשון. Bayis Rishon. So this משנה Mishnah addresses the fact
that they did not have it in the בית שני. Bayis Sheni.
משניטלו הארון, mishenitlo ha-Aron, from the time the ארון Aron was removed,
אבן היתה שם, even hayetah sham, there was a stone there מימות
נביאים ראשונים, mi-yemot nevi'im rishonim, and that stone, it was already there
even from the time of the ארון, Aron, from the time of
the early prophets. You know, so of course if that's true, what,
was the ארון Aron sitting on top of the stone? Was it
that the stone was uncovered, you know, after the ארון Aron was
removed, was it like beneath the ground and they had uncovered it?
It extends from one place to another. When you say it was
there from the time of the נביאים ראשונים, nevi'im rishonim, it doesn't
mean that it was somewhere else. Okay, all the rocks were there
in the world from the time of the נביאים ראשונים. nevi'im rishonim.
It was there, so it's not exactly... Does it extend from the
תהום רבא? Tehom Rabba? Presumably, I mean that's, you know, it המשיח.
ha-Mashiach. Okay, ושתייה היתה נקראת, ve-shtiyah hayetah nikreit, I understand it could
have been underground though, ושתייה היתה נקראת, ve-shtiyah hayetah nikreit, you know,
and it was called the שתייה, Shtiyah, the foundation stone. גבוה מן
הארץ שלש אצבעות, gavoha min ha-aretz shalosh etzba'ot, three fingerbreadths above the
ground. So that's not too much, that's like an inch. So that's
not a very big stone. Now I don't know, I heard, maybe
your footnote would also say where, I don't know where this comes
from, that what it actually means is not that the stone was
only three fingerbreadths, it means that it actually
hovered above the ground miraculously. You can take a look at the
footnote says that, that's not what the word says. Now the rock
of the dome of the rock is pretty big, right? How big
is it? It's huge.
There's a picture in my head.
Yeah, okay.
Isn't it that it extends of, I thought it extended a while,
not that it just goes three inches high, it means it goes
very far. It could. That's why it's גדולה. gedolah.
Right. Oh, yeah yeah, I'm not questioning the גדולה, gedolah, I'm just
questioning the fact that the dome of the rock, if that's what
it is, is much taller, so that so that I don't know.
Anyway, okay.
But the topography has changed. Yeah, that's true also. Could have been
that it got, that there was below the a lot of most
of it was below the
ground and that got exposed. Or right, anyway and there's... we don't
know where the קדש הקדשים Kodesh Ha-Kodashim was. Well first of all,
you have to first assume we're identifying
the אבן שתייה Even Shtiyah with the dome of the rock.
So I don't know. I mean there's a logical reason to make
that identification, they're both supposed to be in the same place, they're
both talking about big rocks. But archaeologists have a pretty good sense
of what the dimensions were and where it was, which is how
you can have פרום frum tours up on הר הבית Har Habayit
because they can avoid going into the עזרה Azarah because they do
have a pretty good sense, you know, about where that was. Yes.
And אבן השתייה, Even Shetiyah, that started long before the ארון Aron
was in in שילה. Shilo. Right? Right? So that's my question. Well,
no, no, no, no, no. It was there, it was on הר
הבית. Har Habayit. It wasn't there where the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
was. The rock was in on that place in הר הבית, Har
Habayit, you know, from but again, my question just is, is that
was the ארון Aron on the rock? Was the rock not yet
uncovered at that time? Okay. Okay, does what's his name, Steinsaltz say
anything about the identifying of the rock with the Dome, with the
rock that was on the rock? He says the Ark was placed
on the rock. Okay, but no, but as to placed the Ark
on the rock, but in terms of identifying it with the Dome,
with the rock. According to many sources, the Dome of the Rock
is אבן השתייה. Even Shetiyah. Many. He doesn't say who the many
are. Okay, fine. All right. Hebrew probably would. All right. Okay, moving
on. Okay. ועליה היה נותן Ve'aleha hayah noten and he would put
the incense on the rock itself. נטל את הדם מי שהיה ממרס.
Natal et hadam mishehayah memares. So now we're done with the incense.
Okay, so he walks backwards. We already said that. Now we're just
sort of footnoting what they would do in the בית שני. Bayit
Sheni. But now he left the עזרה Azarah after doing the incense.
So he gets the blood of the ox from the one who
was stirring it. Remember this guy was stirring it by the steps
leading up to the אולם Ulam or the עזרה. Azarah. נטל את
הדם מי שהיה ממרס בו. Natal et hadam mishehayah memares bo. נכנס
למקום שנכנס. Nichnas lemakom shenichnas. He enters where he had entered. He
goes back with the whole curtain thing to be now by in
front of the ארון Aron or in front of the rock. ועמד
במקום שעמד. Ve'amad bemakom she'amad. He stands where he stood. והזה ממנו
Vehizah mimenu and he sprinkled אחת למעלה ושבע למטה achat lemalah vesheva
lematah one up and seven down. ולא היה מתכוון להזות. Velo hayah
mitkavein lehazot. He wasn't trying to sprinkle on the ארון Aron or
on the rock itself. לא למעלה ולא למטה. Lo lemalah velo lematah.
Not that one should be high, one drop of blood should hit
high and one should hit low.
That wasn't the point of high and low that he was trying
to make the blood hit at a high point and at a
low point. אלא כמצליף Ela kematzlif like a, like a, you know,
what? Flicking? Like a flicking. Yeah, that would be a good translation.
We'll worry about that tomorrow. We're not going to... we're going to
focus... tomorrow we're going to get to the act of the sprinkling.
וכך היה מונה. Vechach hayah moneh. And here's how he would count.
אחת Achat one, the one above.
אחת אחת ואחת אחת ושתיים אחת ושלוש אחת
וארבע אחת וחמש אחת ושש אחת ושבע.
Achat achat ve'achat achat veshtayim achat
veshalosh achat
ve'arba achat vechamesh achat veshesh achat vesheva. Okay. So יצא והניחו על
כן הזהב. Yatza vehinicho al kan hazahav. He went down and he
put the
blood of the ox on a little gold pedestal שבהיכל shebeheichal that
was
in the היכל, Heichal, presumably near the entrance to the קודש הקודשים.
Kodesh Hakodashim.
We're going to mix anymore?
We're going to... הביאו לו את השעיר. Hevi'u lo et hasa'ir. Now,
he has not yet שחט shachted the goat, remember? And I also
want to remind you, he doesn't do a וידוי Viduy on the
goat that's for כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. He only does a וידוי
Viduy on the goat that gets sent לעזאזל. La'azazel. But the one
that has the parallel עבודה Avodah of the ox, although he did
two וידוי Viduy on the ox, he doesn't do a וידוי Viduy
on the goat. All he had done with that goat until now
is drawn the lots. Now you take this goat, שחטו, shachto, he
שחט shachts it, וקיבל במזרק את דמו, vekibel bamazrek et damo, he
also does the קבלת הדם, Kabbalas Hadam, he captures the blood in
a bowl. נכנס למקום שנכנס. Nichnas lemakom shenichnas. He goes back to
where he went. ועמד במקום שעמד. Ve'amad bemakom she'amad. He stood where
he stood. Inside the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. He's back in the
קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. והזה ממנו אחת למעלה ושבע למטה Vehizah mimenu
achat lemalah vesheva lematah וכך היה מונה vechach hayah moneh אחת אחת
ואחת אחת ושתיים וכולי. achat achat ve'achat achat veshtayim vechulu. Okay, the
משנה Mishnah probably had it all,
but the... when they wrote it back, when they put it into
the בבלי, Bavli, they decided to shorten it a bit. Presumably he's
מצליף matzlif here too, right? Even though it didn't say. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. He does the exact same thing. יצא והניחו על כן הזהב.
Yatza vehinicho al kan hazahav. He went out and now put it
similarly on the gold pedestal,
השני, hasheni, excuse me, a second gold pedestal שבהיכל. shebeheichal.
ורבי יהודה אומר לא היה שם אלא כן אחד בלבד.
Verabbi
Yehudah omer
lo hayah sham ela kan echad bilvad. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
says there was only one pedestal. נטל דם הפר והניח דם השעיר.
Natal dam hapar vehiniach dam hasa'ir. Now this is presumably part of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah's statement. Why you only need one pedestal. Because
first of all, it could be a big pedestal that could have
two bowls on it. But also he says you put one down
and you take the other off. So you only need one pedestal.
Okay, so he puts the... down the blood of the goat and
he takes off the blood of the ox, the vessel with the
blood of the ox. And now, yes. Is this שעיר se'ir slaughtered
in the היכל? Heichal? No, no, no, no. He left the היכל.
Heichal. Doesn't say that he left? Doesn't say. It's a good point.
It's a good point. He doesn't say that he left. But he
did leave. Okay. He did not... you're right. It doesn't say that
he left. Just a good point. They brought him. I know. But
he didn't. I mean, we'll see it in the גמרא. Gemara. You're
right. It's missing. You're right. That is bizarre. I hadn't noticed that.
You want to just read the note here? What does the note
say? Go for it. Yeah. Okay. It says they don't bring the
goat inside the היכל; Heichal; rather, he leaves the היכל Heichal for
the courtyard and they bring
it
to him there.
And then he re-enters. All right. Yeah. You're right. It's not there,
but that's clearly
what
happened. You don't do... So now he took the, he put down
the blood of the goat, he took the blood of the פר,
par,
and והזה ממנו על הפרוכת שכנגד הארון. ve-hizah mimenu al ha-parochet she-keneged
ha-aron. And now he does the sprinkling, he's outside the קודש קדשים,
Kodesh Kodashim, he does the sprinkling on the on the curtain in
the space of the curtain that is opposite the ארון, Aron, the
middle of the
curtain. מבחוץ, mibachutz, standing outside the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. אחת למעלה
ושבע למטה ולא היה מתכוון וכולי, achat le-ma'alah ve-sheva le-matah ve-lo hayah
mitkaven ve-chulu, one above, seven below, he would not try to hit
above and below, but he would be flicking, we'll see what that
means. וכך היה מונה וכולי, ve-kach hayah moneh ve-chulu, he would count
the following. נטל דם השעיר והניח דם הפר, natal dam ha-sa'ir ve-hiniach
dam ha-par, then he took the blood of the goat, put the
blood of the cow back on the pedestal, either the same one
or the other pedestal. והזה ממנו על הפרוכת שכנגד הארון מבחוץ אחת
למעלה ושבע למטה וכולי, ve-hizah mimenu al ha-parochet she-keneged ha-aron mibachutz achat
le-ma'alah ve-sheva le-matah ve-chulu, and then he did the same with the
blood of the goat on the curtain opposite the
ארון. Aron. עירה דם הפר לתוך דם השעיר, irah dam ha-par le-toch
dam ha-sa'ir, he now mixed the two bloods together. ונתן את המלא
בריקן, ve-natan et ha-malei ba-reikan, and now you sort of pour one,
you pour one into the other and now you have one full
vessel that has both, and then you pour from the full vessel
that has both back into the empty vessel. You know, if you're
trying to mix things well, you pour them from vessel to vessel.
So that's what he did.
Like a bartender. No original שבע ברכות.
Sheva Brachot. Exactly,
I was thinking exactly about that. Talking about שבע ברכות, Sheva Brachot,
we're going to have some very interesting, we're going to have some
very interesting אגדתא Aggadta coming up. Let's take a look. משנגנז לא
תני, mishe-nignaz lo tani, it did not say from the time the
ארון Aron was hidden, which is what we've been assuming until now,
אלא משניטל, ela mishe-nital, from the time the ארון Aron was taken,
which might mean taken away. תנא כמאן דאמר ארון גלה לבבל, tana
ke-man de-amar aron galah le-vavel, so this is not the idea that
the ארון Aron was hidden in the מקדש, Mikdash, it's that the
ארון Aron actually was brought into exile into Babylonia. דתניא, de-tanya, as
it says in a בריתא, Baraita, רבי אליעזר אומר ארון גלה לבבל,
Rabbi Eliezer omer aron galah le-vavel, the ארון Aron was exiled to
בבל. Bavel. שנאמר ולתשובת השנה שלח המלך נבוכדנצר ויביאהו בבל עם כלי
חמדת בית ה', she-ne'emar u-litshuvat ha-shanah shalach ha-melech Nevuchadnezzar va-yeviehu vavel im
klei chemdat beit Hashem, at the end of the year, the return
of the year, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar sent, ויביאהו בבל, va-yeviehu vavel, and he
brought him, meaning צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu,
I think is what it's talking
about, no, יהויכין, Yehoyachin, excuse me, into בבל Bavel עם כלי חמדת
בית ה', im klei chemdat beit Hashem, with the desirous vessels of
the house of God. What's the most desirous vessel? It's the ארון,
Aron, so the ארון Aron was taken into exile. רבי שמעון בן
יוחי אומר ארון גלה לבבל, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer aron galah
le-vavel, the ארון Aron was, so another position, a similar position, the
ארון Aron was exiled. שנאמר לא יותר דבר אמר ה', she-ne'emar lo
yivater davar amar Hashem, nothing will be left, said God, after the
exile. So what's דבר? davar? אלו עשרת הדברות שבאו, elu aseret ha-dibrot
she-bau, the ten commandments that are written in the לוחות luchot that
are in the ארון. Aron. רבי יהודה בן לקיש אומר ארון במקומו
נגנז, Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish omer aron bi-mekomo nignaz, no, the ארון
Aron was buried and hidden in its place underneath the floor presumably
of the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. שנאמר ויאריכו הבדים מן הקודש על
פני הדביר, she-ne'emar va-ya'arichu ha-badim min ha-kodesh al pnei ha-dvir,
the tops of the poles were be able were seen in the
holy space, in the היכל, Heichal, by the face of the דביר,
dvir, the דביר dvir is the wall that separates the קודש Kodesh
and the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So they would poke out through
the curtain or they would create protrusions, bumps in the curtain. ולא
יראו החוצה, ve-lo yera'u ha-chutzah, they would not actually be seen, but
they would be protruding. ויהיו שם עד היום הזה, va-yihyu sham ad
ha-yom ha-zeh, and it would be and it was there, they were
there until this day. So until this day means until any day
you read the פסוק, pasuk, they're still there until today. ופליגא דעולא,
u-pliga de-Ulla, it argues on עולא. Ulla. דאמר עולא שאל רבי מתיא
בן חרש את רבי שמעון בן יוחי. de-amar Ulla sha'al Rabbi Matya
ben Charash et Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So again, this is Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai that said that it was buried there, but now
we have עולא Ulla that's going to tell that according to Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai it was not buried there, it was exiled. That
we have Rabbi Matya ben Charash ask Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai ברומי,
be-Romi, when they were in Rome. So that's interesting, you know, when
you're in Rome, you're wondering, you're thinking about all the stuff that
was taken in the exile and then you know sort of maybe
taken over by Rome, what's being hidden in the treasuries of the
Vatican.
וכי מאחר שרבי אליעזר מלמדנו פעם ראשונה ושנייה ארון גלה לבבל, ve-chi
me-achar she-Rabbi Eliezer melamdenu pa'am rishonah u-shniyah aron galah le-vavel, after Rabbi
Eliezer teaches us first and second time the ארון Aron was exiled
into בבל. Bavel. Because one thing by the way, right, it was
exiled into בבל Bavel in the first בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash, obviously
they didn't have it in the second. Meaning ראשונה ושנייה, rishonah u-shniyah,
meaning that there are two פסוקים psukim that teach us that by
the end of the first בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash it was taken
into בבל. Bavel. ראשונה היא דאמרן, rishonah hi de-amran, the first one
as we said, ויביאהו בבל עם כלי חמדת בית ה'. va-yeviehu vavel
im klei chemdat beit Hashem. שנייה מאי היא, shniyah mai hi, what
about the second one? דכתיב ויצא מבת ציון כל הדרה. de-chtiv va-yeitzei
mi-bat Tzion kol hadarah. So now I'm sorry, I completely said wrong,
not first and second, what was exiled in the first בית המקדש,
Beit Ha-Mikdash, obviously they didn't have it in the second. Meaning ראשונה
ושנייה, rishonah u-shniyah, meaning that there are two פסוקים psukim that teach
us that by the end of the first בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash
it was taken into בבל. Bavel. One is the verse we already
quoted, the all of the desirous vessels means the ארון, Aron, and
the other, ויצא מבת ציון כל הדרה, va-yeitzei mi-bat Tzion kol hadarah,
from the daughter of Zion was taken out all of her glory.
So and how does that mean? So again for us of course
that means the most important thing, the ארון, Aron, but now we're
going to have another דרשה drashah that particularly underscores that.
מאי כל הדרה? mai kol hadarah? חדרה. chadarah. So what's in the
חדר, cheder, what's in the innermost chamber? Right like
הביאני המלך חדריו, heviani ha-melech chadarav, and actually we're going to see
some quotes from שיר השירים, Shir Ha-Shirim, right, חדריו הביאני המלך חדריו,
chadarav heviani ha-melech chadarav, so the idea of in the chamber. Innermost
chamber, so that's what was taken out. So we have two פסוקים
pesukim to teach us that in the בית ראשון Bayis Rishon the
ארון aron was taken. אתה
מאי אתה אומר? ata mai ata omer? You, what do you say?
Meaning, what's your position? Do you agree that it was taken into
בבל? Bavel? אמר ליה amar lei so רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai said back to him no, שאני אומר, she-ani omer,
I say, ארון במקומו נגנז, aron bimkomo nignaz, it wasn't taken into
בבל, Bavel, it was buried in its place. שנאמר ויאריכו הבדים shene-emar
vayarichu habadim like we said before ויהיו שם עד היום הזה, vayiyu
sham ad hayom hazeh, it was there until today. So anyway, so
that's how it argues on עולא. Ulla. עולא Ulla claims that according
to רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai it was, it's
there, whereas the other, the ברייתא Braitah said that according to רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai it was exiled. So two
versions we're not going to answer it two versions of what רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai said. Now, אמר ליה רבה
לעולא, amar lei Rabba le-Ulla, so רבה Rabba said to עולא, Ulla,
מאי משמע, mai mashma, where do you get from this verse that
it's still there? דכתיב ויהיו שם עד היום הזה. dchtiv vayiyu sham
ad hayom hazeh. So now we're going to challenge that.
וכל היכא דכתיב עד היום הזה לעולם הוא? vechol heicha de-chtiv ad
hayom hazeh le-olam hu? Does that really mean until now as opposed
to until today when the verse was being written? Is it really
mean forever? והכתיב, vehachtiv, there will give you other פסוקים pesukim that
say
עד היום הזה. ad hayom hazeh. ואת היבוסי יושב ירושלים לא הורישו
בני בנימין, ve-es hayevusi yoshev Yerushalayim lo horishu benei Binyamin, the children
of בנימין Binyamin did not sort of conquer, וישב היבוסי את בני
בנימין בירושלים עד היום הזה. vayeishev hayevusi es benei Binyamin beYerushalayim ad
hayom hazeh. And the Jebusites sat with בני בנימין benei Binyamin until
today. So now you think what they're going to challenge is that
there's no Jebusites in Jerusalem, but that we're not going to challenge.
Who knows who the non-Jews are in Jerusalem. But it also suggests
that בני בנימין benei Binyamin was in Jerusalem for forever. But that's
not true. הכי נמי דלא גלו? hachi nami delo galu? Are you
trying to tell me that בני בנימין benei Binyamin were not exiled
from Jerusalem?
והתניא, vehatanya, we heard in a ברייתא, Braitah, רבי יהודה אומר חמשים
ושתים שנה לא עבר איש ביהודה, Rabbi Yehuda omer chamishim u-shtayim shana
lo avar ish bi-Yehuda, for the fifty-two years of exile although we
speak about seventy years of exile, actually it's only fifty-two years after
the חורבן churban of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash according to חז"ל.
Chazal. It was seventy years after, the seventy years is seventy years
from the time that צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu was taken into exile, but only
eighteen years after that was the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash destroyed. So
it was actually fifty-two years from the destruction of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So for those fifty-two years לא עבר איש ביהודה, lo
avar ish bi-Yehuda, no man passed through יהודה, Yehuda, presumably not Jew
or non-Jew. שנאמר על ההרים אשא בכי ונהי ועל נאות מדבר קינה,
shene-emar al he-harim esa vechi vanahi ve-al ne-os midbar kina, on the
mountains I will lift up cry and
wailing and a eulogy in
the wilderness, כי נצתו מבלי איש עובר ki nitzesu mibli ish over
מה? ma? ולא שמעו קול מקנה, ve-lo sham'u kol mikneh, because they
have been desolated from any man passing through and they not heard
the sound of the flock, מעוף השמים ועד בהמה נדדו הלכו, me-of
hashamayim ve-ad behema nadedu halachu, from the sky of the heaven until
animal they have wandered and left. So there have been nobody there.
And how do you know for fifty-two years? בהמה behema בגימטריה begematria
חמשים ושתים הוו chamishim u-shtayim havu
because בהמה behema in גימטריה gematria is fifty-two. Now obviously they already
knew fifty-two, but they tied it to this verse and therefore they
said that this verse is that it's completely desolate, there's absolutely nobody
there. One minute. והתניא, vehatanya, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, שבע
שנים נתקיים גפרית ומלח בארץ ישראל. sheva shanim niskaima gofris va-melach be-Eretz
Yisrael. The פסוק pasuk says about the exile גפרית ומלח שרפה כל
ארצה, gofris va-melach sereifa kol artzah, sulfur and salt. So he says
for seven years that was true in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that
the land was not only was there no people living there but
the land was completely untilable, destroyed. ואמר רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא דרבי
יוסי? ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yosei? Where does he get
this idea that seven years? אתיא ברית ברית, atia bris bris, he
makes a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shava. כתיב הכא והגביר ברית לרבים שבוע
אחד chtiv hacha ve-higbir bris lerabbim shavua echad and so the way
רש"י Rashi says this is being read is that
נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar sort of imposed the ברית bris on the masses or
on the great ones for one week, for a seven-year period. וכתיב
vechtiv and what ברית bris is that? The ברית bris that says
ואמרו על אשר עזבו את ברית ה' אלהי אבותם. ve-omru al asher
azvu es bris Hashem Elokei avosam. Why is this happening? Why is
the land destroyed? Because they abandoned the ברית. bris. So that was
for connecting to this verse of seven years, that punishment of
גפרית ומלח gofris va-melach was for seven years. Okay, so anyway, so
that's the question. So you see even though it says they were
there עד היום הזה ad hayom hazeh for the Jebusites and for
בני בנימין, benei Binyamin, they were not there for a period of
time. So עד היום הזה ad hayom hazeh does not mean without
cease. So the גמרא Gemara says he has an answer. אמר ליה
הכא כתיב שם. amar lei hacha chtiv sham. It says ויהיו שם
עד היום הזה, vayiyu sham ad hayom hazeh, there. שם sham somehow
means continuously. התם לא כתיב שם, hatam lo chtiv sham, it didn't
say there they were until today, so somehow that doesn't have to
mean continuous. מאי בין הכא להתם?
mai ben
hacha le-hatam?
What? By the ארון aron it says ויהיו שם עד היום הזה
vayiyu sham ad hayom hazeh and by בני בנימין benei Binyamin it
says וישב היבוסי עד היום הזה vayeishev hayevusi ad hayom hazeh without
שם. sham. So somehow שם sham means that it was permanent and
continuous. I don't exactly get why שם sham has to do with
continuity of time as opposed to continuity of place, but that's what
he says the difference is. Yes, Charlie.
The obvious meaning of עד היום הזה ad hayom hazeh would be
meaning until the time that the author...
That's what I said. The פשט, pshat, right. Exactly.
So how this would not make sense to have that discussion if
that's...
I understand but they assume that once it's canonized and in the
תנ״ך, Tanakh, then it will always be true and it will always
be היום הזה. hayom hazeh. That was the argument as long as
it says somehow the word שם, sham, that makes the difference. Okay.
Does the
היום הזה hayom hazeh can mean until the day of the...
Yeah, well that's why the according to the position that the ארון
aron is still there. So we're not done. So גמרא Gemara says
וכל היכא דכתיב שם לעולם הוא, vechol heicha dechtiv sham leolam hu,
you really mean every time it says שם sham until today that
it means לעולם? leolam? מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this. ומהם
מן בני בנימין Umehem min bnei binyamin and from the people of
בנימין Binyamin הלכו להר שעיר, halchu lehar seir, they went to the
הר שעיר, Har Seir, אנשים חמש מאות, anashim chamesh meot, five hundred
people, ופלטיה ונעריה ורפיה ועוזיאל בני ישעי בראשם upalatyav ve’naaryav verafayav ve’uzyav
bnei yishai berosham and these four people were heading them. ויכו את
שארית הפליטה לעמלק Vayakku et sheerit hapleita la’amalek and they wiped out
the remnant that was from עמלק, Amalek, וישבו שם עד היום הזה
vayeshvu sham ad hayom hazeh they remained there until today. So how
could it be that they are still there in הר שעיר Har
Seir until today? וכבר עלה סנחריב מלך אשור ובלבל את כל הארצות
Uchevar alasem sancheiriv melech ashur uvilbel et kol ha’aratzot when סנחריב Sancheiriv
came he re, you know, he put everybody in a different place
from where they were so nobody is where they were originally. שנאמר
ואסיר גבולות עמים, Shene’emar ve’asir gevulot amim, I will remove the boundaries
of
nations, ואתודותיהם שושיתי ve’atudoteihem shoshosti and their, I don't know how to
translate that, I forgot I looked it up before hand. Their what?
Some... and
I plunder their treasures. Okay, anyway so you see that that it
does not mean שם sham does not mean that they continued to
be there until today. So it says where are we? תיובתא, Tyuvta,
alright, the problem. So שם sham does not mean it's literally until
today and you do not have a support from that verse. He
still might believe the ארון aron is buried there, but he doesn't
have a support from that verse. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, תנא, tana, we taught in a ברייתא,
beraisa, וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, the sages say, ארון בלשכת דיר העצים
היה. aron belishkat dir ha’etzim haya. This is what we learned before
when we learned שקלים Shekalim and elsewhere that the ארון aron was
not taken into exile was not buried under the קודש קדשים, kodesh
kodashim, it was actually buried in the chamber where they had the
wood that they used for the מזבח mizbe'ach under the floor. היה
גנוז, Haya ganuz, that's where it was buried. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan
nami tanina, we taught here the משנה Mishna in שקלים Shekalim which
is why we learned שקלים Shekalim before יומא. Yoma. מעשה בכהן אחד
שהיה מתעסק Ma’aseh bekohen echad shehaya mitasek וראה רצפה משונה מחברותיה, vera’a
ritzpa meshuna mechavrateha, a כהן kohen was just, you know, busying himself
with something or playing with fooling around and he saw that the
floor was different in one place from the other places. I assumed
it meant like the color, the tile was different, it looked dug
up. רש״י Rashi says it means that the tile was a little
bit higher so he could tell that it had been dug up
because it was a little bit uneven tile. ובא להודיע לחבירו, Uva
lehodi’a lechaveiro, he went and he told his friend, ולא הספיק לגמור
את הדבר velo hispik ligmor et hadavar and he did not was
not able to finish getting the words out where the ארון aron
was buried or where it was buried, עד שיצאה נשמתו ad sheyatza
nishmato until his soul was con was you know left him. He
dropped dead. וידעו בייחוד ששם נגנז Veyadu beyichud shesham nignaz so they
knew maybe they didn't know where in the דיר העצים dir ha’etzim
or maybe actually did get the words out of his mouth but
they knew that the ארון aron was buried in the דיר העצים.
dir ha’etzim. In the in the לשכת העצים. lishkat ha’etzim. Okay. מאי
הוה עביד, Mai hava avid,
it says he was fooling around. What was he doing? אמר רבי
חלבו מתעסק בקרדומו היה. Amar Rabbi Chelbo mitasek bekardumo haya. Oh I
don't know how he knows he was playing with his axe. איך
נישט. ich nisht. Okay. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael
we taught the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael what? Yeah he
was chopping wood, right. תניא... Tanya...
but I don't know somehow playing with the axe made him I
don't know how that led him finding it. I don't know why
of all things he decided
to identify that as what he was doing. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל
Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael מאי הוה עביד mai hava avid now we
have a ברייתא beraisa that says, I'm sorry I skipped a line.
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael שני כהנים בעלי מומין
היו מתלין, shnei kohanim ba’alei mumim hayu matlin, here's a different version
or an elaborated version of the story. There are two כהנים kohanim
that had blemishes so they could not be working in the מקדש.
Mikdash. So you know what they did? They used to like you
know they sent them to peel potatoes. You know so not really
so they sent them to to go to the chamber of the
wood and to get rid of all of the wood that had
that had worms in it. To dispose of the wormy wood. To
go through stick by stick and dispose of the wormy wood. היו
מתלין בעצים hayu matlin be’etzim they were removing the worms or the
wormy wood from the wood. ונשמטה קרדומו של אחד מהם Venishmeta kardumo
shel echad mehem and this is where we have the story about
the about the axe. The axe of one of them slipped mehem
and נפלה שם nafla sham and it fell there meaning basically it
hit the floor presumably underneath where the ארון aron was. ויצאה אש
ואכלתו Veyatza esh va’achaltato and a fire came out of the floor
and consumed him. It's like space... right... I could be him. I
assume I could be the axe but I assume to make it
consistent with the previous story it's him.
And then maybe then he noticed and said something else oh what's
that a fire coming out.
As opposed to the other guy noticing. I don't know maybe. All
right. I assumed it meant him. Anyway. Straight out of Indiana Jones.
They say the axe.
Okay. They say the axe but then they say see however יצחק
עיניים Yitzchak Einayim says ירושלים Yerushalayim is probably something. All right whatever
fine.
Moving on. All right.
רב יהודה רמי. Rav Yehuda rami. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda showed a
contradiction. כתיב Ktiv one verse says ויאריכו ראשי הבדים vayari’u rashei habadim
that the heads of the poles will be seen were seen. וכתיב
Uchtiv another verse says ולא יראו החוצה velo yeira’u hachutza they were
not seen. הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? So what does it mean were
they seen or not seen? נראין ואין נראין. Nirin ve’ein nirin. They
were seen but they were not fully seen. What does What does
that mean? תניא נמי הכא, Tanya nami hacha, we taught similarly, ויראו
ראשי הבדים, Vayir'u rashei habadim, they were seen. יכול, לא יזזו ממקומן,
yakhol lo yezazu mimkoman, maybe it means that they were not moved
from their place because the ארון, Aron, right, the ארון Aron was—this
is the קודש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, right, and this is the ארון,
Aron, well it's not exactly square, but you get the idea. The
ארון Aron only took up a small part of the קודש הקדשים,
Kodesh Hakodashim, and even with the staves, it would not have been—the
קודש הקדשים Kodesh Hakodashim was 20 אמות, amot, right, 20 אמות amot
by 20 אמות amot we said. The ארון Aron was like what
like you know אמתיים וחצי, amatayim vachetzi, two and a half אמות.
amot. So even however long the staves were, they weren't like 10
אמות amot long on each side. So if the staves stayed in
their places, they would not have gotten up to the front of—and
this was dead center—it would not have gotten up to the curtain,
it would not have gotten up to the front of the קודש
הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. So יכול Yakhol, לא יזזו ממקומן, lo yezazu mimkoman,
perhaps they would not be moved from their—they would be like you
know exactly where they should be alongside the ארון. Aron. תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, where am I? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, ויאריכו הבדים, vaya'arichu
habadim, they were lengthened, which now you could say that means somehow
miraculously they were lengthened. The Maharsha makes it sound no, all it
means would be that they actually would move the staves so they
would not be centered. They would be still in the you know
the sockets or the loops or whatever the rings that were alongside,
but they would not be evenly centered. They'd be basically pushed
forward, we're going to see, but they'd be pushed forward so that
the tops of the staves while it's still alongside the ארון Aron
the tops of the staves could reach the wall the curtain of
the קודש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. Okay so he says so ויאריכו הבדים
vaya'arichu habadim they were lengthened, they were moved forward. They were long
but they weren't 20 אמות amot long, maybe they were 10 אמות
amot long or 12 אמות amot long. Okay.
יכול יהיו מקרעין בפרוכת, Yakhol yehu makar'in baparochet, maybe that now that
they were going up to the front of the curtain maybe they
would tear through the curtain and come out. תלמוד לומר ולא יראו
החוצה, Talmud lomar velo yera'u hachutza, they would not be seen. So
they were pushing against the curtain but they were not visible. הכיצד,
Ha keitzad, so what was happening? דוחקין ובולטין
ויוצאין בפרוכת, Dochkin uvoltin veyotzin baparochet,
so they would push and protrude and like and they would be
not coming out but they would like be making a you know
a bump in the פרוכת. parochet. ונראין כשני דדי אשה, Venireen kishnei
dadei isha,
and it would look like a woman's breasts. So you would sort
of see the outline of it without actually seeing them, שנאמר, shene'emar,
צרור המור דודי לי בין שדי ילין, Tzror hamor dodi li bein
shadai yalin, quoting a verse from שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim, a bundle
of myrrh my beloved is to me he will rest between my
breasts. So seeing now that becomes and this is going to be
the next piece of what we're going to learn a very erotic
imagery of the ארון Aron and the relationship of בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael to God, you know which is what שיר השירים Shir Hashirim
is. It's in not just romantic but even erotic and you know
in a way that's extremely powerful. It calls on like some of
our most powerful like urges which is also like this desire to
unify and to connect with somebody else in a very powerful way
and translates that into the context of you know of God and
בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Look we know that you know in other
traditions like in Eastern traditions and in Islam you know there was
a lot of sort of erotic in India right a lot of
erotic poetry in the sense of you know
intersecting with religious and sort of bringing those two together. I mean
the only thing we sort of have clearly of that is the
whole שיר השירים Shir Hashirim you know but it gets played out
in some of the descriptions that we're about to deal with in
terms of the ארון Aron and the קודש הקדשים Kodesh Hakodashim and
God and בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. And I want to say something
about that which is the power of remember we said before that
it said חדרא חדרא chadra chadra by the by the ארון Aron
and you know I quoted before "Heviani hamelech chadarav", הביאני המלך חדריו.
Heviani hamelech chadarav. So who is going in to the innermost chamber?
It's the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So
thinking about the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
going in as right to the innermost chamber of the you know
of the beloved you know the bedroom where God here as the
woman which by the way is also worth pointing out that most
of the imagery God is the man and בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
is the woman. Here God becomes the woman like the object if
you would the you know of desire right and the and the
one that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is now entering into her
chambers where you know she sort of you see the feminine form
right protruding out with the ארון Aron and entering in. And it's
actually this verse right צרור המור דודי לי בין שדי ילין. Tzror
hamor dodi li bein shadai yalin. מור Mor is a קטורת, ketoret,
it's an incense. So and you put the קטורת ketoret between the
בדים, badim, בין שדי ילין. bein shadai yalin. So that's exactly what
you're doing. You're going in to be one sleep with as it
were you know the beloved and placing the מור mor right there
בין הבדים. bein habadim. So it's really very powerful in translating this
imagery of שיר השירים Shir Hashirim to this meaning of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol entering into the קודש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. And again
I don't know if this is intended or not but You might
have, I didn't note it at the time, but you might have
noted that when we talked about entering in the קדש הקדשים Kodesh
Hakodashim without a purpose, the phrase used was ביאה ריקנית. Bia Rekanit.
ביאה, Bia, right, entering in, right which is the same, right, which
is the same word for intercourse, right? So there's very powerful erotic
imagery here, particularly around this entering into the Holy of Holies, the
innermost chambers. And I really think the placing, I don't know, somebody
else must have said this before me, but the idea of placing
the incense between the בדים, Badim, צרור המור דודי לי בין שדי
ילין, Tzror hamor dodi li bein shadai yalin, is like seems to
be very much being, you know, indicated here. אמר רב קטינא, Amar
Rav Ketina, so said Rav Ketina, בשעה שישראל עולים לרגל, Beshah sheYisrael
olim laregel, when Israel would go up for the רגל, Regel, מגלים
להם את הפרוכת, Megallin lahem et haparochet, they would they would pull
aside, roll up the curtain in the קדש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. Now
how they would see that because they weren't allowed in the היכל
Heichal either, but if you remember all the doors of the היכל
Heichal and the עזרה Azarah were all in a line. So presumably
they would like pull aside the curtains of all of the doors
and they could see straight into the קדש הקדשים Kodesh Hakodashim even
if they were in the עזרה. Azarah. Okay, and they would do
this, ומראים להם את הכרובים שהיו מעורים זה בזה, Umareem lahem et
hakruvim shehayu meurim zeh bazeh, and now we're trans, now this is
going to play out in terms of the כרובים Kruvim which were
two angels or two human forms, and they saw them that they
weren't just standing opposite. Somehow miraculously they were intertwined one
another. I mean you see that in like right Greek and Roman
art, right, you know, don't you know how they draw these like
figures like intertwined lovers intertwined, and they said to them ואומרים להם,
V'omrim lahem, ראו חיבתכם לפני המקום, Re'u chibatchem lifnei hamakom, see your
beloved you are before God, כחיבת זכר ונקבה, Kechibat zachar unekevah, if
you needed it spelled out anymore, like the love between male and
female. Also that phrase זכר ונקבה Zachar unekevah is very, no not
איש ואישה, Ish v'ishah, right, is very much, you know, physical and
sexual, right, much more than even איש ואישה. Ish v'ishah. Now what's
of course a little bit of a challenge here beyond just the
erotic imagery is that the exposing of it, right, that isn't that
sort of like ruining the whole thing? Isn't the whole point that
it takes place in the private and in the Holy of Holies,
the most intimate of acts? But you're obviously dealing with the problem
of how do you let other people than the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know, sort of be, you
know, you know, get, be
impacted by this whole by this reality? So you have this idea
of almost like peeking into the
bedroom.
The blood on the פרוכת Parochet plays into the...
oh that's interesting. What, you mean like like hymenal bleeding? Like like...
oh that's a very interesting thought. That's very interesting. Wow. I hadn't
gone that far. Oh, that's very interesting. Okay. מתיב רב חסדא, Metiv
Rav Chisda, so Rav Chisda asked, ולא יבואו לראות כבלע את הקודש.
V'lo yavo'u lir'ot k'vala et hakodesh. Now how could you say that
they exposed it like this? I mean we have in the... in
the משכן, Mishkan, it says that before the לויים Levi'im were to
come to carry the... to carry the vessels, they could not see
as the vessels were being put away into the... into the, you
know, into the bags. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב, V'amar Rav Yehudah
amar Rav, בשעת הכנסת כלים לנרתק, Besh'at hachnasat kelim lenartek, when the
vessels were being put into their
various... bags שלהם, Shelahem, they could not, and that's what the verse
means, they could not go and see it. And here you're talking
about this type of exposure? אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, משל
לכלה, Mashal lekallah, it's like a bride, כל זמן שהיא בבית אביה,
Kol zeman shehi beveit aviha, as long as she's in her father's
house, meaning even after קידושין, Kiddushin, but they hadn't started living together,
it's not yet נישואין. Nisu'in. So she's still living in her father's
house. צנועה מבעלה, Tzenuah miba'alah, she's very... she's very modest. She's very,
you know, even though the man is her husband, they haven't started
living together yet, so she doesn't expose herself. כיון שבאה לבית חמיה,
Keivan sheba'ah leveit chamia, once she comes to her father-in-law's house, which
is quite funny, it really means her חתן's Chatan house, but you
know, but meant, but the חתן Chatan was living with his father.
So once it's נישואין, Nisu'in, אינה צנועה מבעלה, Einah tzenuah miba'alah, then
she's not so, you know,
modest with her husband and therefore she's willing to allow herself to
be seen more. Now of course what's amazing about sort of the
answer is, in the time of the משכן, Mishkan, they were just
married. בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and God were just married. So God
had to adopt more privacy. And by the way, if it was
unclear before, God is here the woman, right? The same way it
was the... the ארון Aron was like the woman and the breast,
God is the woman. So when they were just married, God was
still very private, you know, while God is dressing and undressing He
doesn't want, you know, to be seen. So, you know, go out,
I gotta, you know, guys, I don't want you to be seeing
the vessels naked, right? Then they've been living out together for a
lot of years and a few hundred years later in the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, now it's okay every now and then, you know,
you remove the curtains and you're able to see. By the way,
what else is sort of
powerful about this is, you know, again, the use of the phrase
בית אביה Beit Aviha and בית חמיה, Beit Chamia, might have just
been a way to say קידושין Kiddushin and נישואין, Nisu'in, but also
if it's בית חמיה, Beit Chamia, so God moving sort of to
הר הבית Har Habayit is moving to... the father-in-law's house. It's almost
like again by casting God as the woman, especially in this patriarchal
society, and the man is therefore the one that sort of is
the one, you know, it's his house, his control, his and she's
entering into that, so it's like the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, I
think there's something how it's like, you know, so much focus that
the מקדש Mikdash is like מקום השכינה, Makom Hashchinah, not our place,
right? But here it's actually you know, the מקדש Mikdash moving in
is like it's moving into our land, moving into our house, you
know, and therefore it's like, you know, we have actually a little
bit
more sense of freedom in this relationship because God is now in
our land as opposed to when we were out in the wilderness,
you know, then we were less בעל הבית. Baal Habayis. So I
think that's also interesting and part of the whole this whole imagery
that it's setting up.
Very empowering sociologically. That's what I'm saying.
Yeah, right, and the irony
is that by projecting God as the woman, sociologically it maintains—Right, it
reinforces, right, it reinforces the patriarchal, right, type of reality but working
within—Working within that reality, it's making—It's very powerful to be casting בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael as the man.
And now God is entering in to בית חמיה, Beis Chamia, yes.
And there's some feminist imagery here
of God as the woman. Yes. Right, yeah, yes. That's the problem
when the challenge for feminists who try to take parts of the
tradition and sort of make them work at a feminist level, but
they're still deeply embedded in the, you know, in the patriarchal, so
like the שכינה, Shekhinah, right, which is the feminine dimension of God
is still, you
know, not as positive as the male dimensions of God within the
Kabbalistic sort of mindset. So it's not so easy to recast those
things. Right, okay, anyway let's read a little bit more. Okay, מתיבי
חנה בר קטינא: Maysivi Chana bar Katina: מעשה בכהן אחד שהיה
מתעסק—What Maaseh b'kohen echad she'haya misasek do you mean that now things
are different? Then how come like this guy died when the fire
went out with the ארון Aron or he tried to tell somebody
things—It seems like it's still that privacy thing. Now of course I
thought the whole story was because you didn't want it to be
known where it was, it wasn't like an ongoing issue of privacy,
but the גמרא Gemara reads it that the reason the fire went
out or whatever happened was because he exposed the ארון, Aron, and
so you see that that idea of privacy is still there. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, נתגרשה קאמרת? Nisgarsha kamart?
What? After they've been divorced? נתגרשה חזרו לחיבתן הראשונה. Nisgarsha chazru l'chibasan
harishonah. They were divorced and then remarried, then it gets back to
the way things used to be. So they were divorced after חורבן
בית ראשון, Churban Bayis Rishon, then comes בית שני, Bayis Sheni, now
they're remarried, so now God wants some privacy again. It's not like
they've been together for so long that they can be so comfortable
with one another. It gets back to the original way it was.
So okay, so now let's finish it up. Okay, במאי אוקימנא? B'mai
okimna? Now what are we talking about? אילימא במקדש ראשון, Ineima b'Mikdash
Rishon, so this idea that the poles would be pushing out of
the curtain. If it's in the first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, מי
הוי פרוכת? mi avi paroches? There wasn't a פרוכת, paroches, it was
a wall. Of course what we're going to say is that yes,
but the doorway of the wall was a hanging curtain. אלא במקדש
שני, Ela b'Mikdash Sheni, it was the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
מי הוי כרובים? mi avi keruvim? There weren't כרובים. keruvim. So לעולם—Oh,
L'olam it's not even the poles protruding, it was also just pulling
back the פרוכת paroches so people could see.
Why were there no כרובים keruvim in בית שני?
Bayis Sheni? Because the כרובים keruvim were on top of the ארון.
Aron. לעולם
במקדש ראשון, L'olam b'Mikdash Rishon, it was the first בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. מאי פרוכת? Mai paroches? פרוכת דבבא, Paroches debava, and the curtain
was the curtain hanging in the doorway. דאמר רבי זירא אמר רב:
De'amar Rabi Zeira amar Rav: שלשה עשר פרוכות הוו במקדש. Shlosha asar
parochos havu b'Mikdash. There were thirteen curtains. שבע כנגד שבעה שערים, Shiva
k'neged shiva shearim, seven opposite the seven in the doorways of the
seven gates that entered into the עזרה. Azarah. שתים, Shtayim, and two
more, אחת בפתחה של היכל, achas b'pischah shel heichal, one curtain
by the gate,
the gate didn't have a—Maybe in addition to a doorway, presumably, right,
two and there were two more, אחת בפתחה של היכל, achas b'pischah
shel heichal, one in the doorway of entering into the היכל, Heichal,
ואחת בפתחה של אולם, v'achas b'pischah shel ulam, and one in the
doorway of the אולם. Ulam. So now we're up to nine. שתים
בדביר, Shtayim b'dvir, two by the דביר—the Dvir קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim
as we said, the two, you know, that were going in different
directions, right, with openings at one end and then openings at the
other. This was by בית שני. Bayis Sheni. This is by בית
שני, Bayis Sheni, but the same way by בית שני Bayis Sheni
you had curtains in the doorway, you had curtains in the doorway
in בית ראשון, Bayis Rishon, that's the argument. ושתים כנגדם בעליות, u'shtayim
k'negdam ba'aliyos, two more on the second story of the קודש קודשים
Kodesh Kodashim you also had two curtains in the story above the
קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim that you would go in to go down
when you had to do work. Okay, anyway we see there were
curtains in the doorways. So yes, this idea of the poles protruding
and removing the curtain is מקדש ראשון Mikdash Rishon with the poles
in the doorways. Okay, so רב אחא בר יעקב אמר: Rav Acha
bar Yaakov amar: לעולם במקדש שני, L'olam b'Mikdash Sheni, really we're talking
about the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, וכרובים דצורה
הוו קיימי, u'keruvim detzura hava kaymi, and actually yes, there were not
actual כרובים, keruvim, meaning the poles of the ארון Aron that was
מקדש ראשון. Mikdash Rishon. But the story about removing the curtain and
seeing the כרובים, keruvim, we're not talking about the like statue כרובים,
keruvim, we're talking about some type of an image of כרובים. keruvim.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, and as it is written This image was painted on
the walls or maybe even carved into the walls. Apparently there were
wood walls that lined the stone, so it was wood paneling lining
the stone and carved into the wood was images of כרובים k'ruvim
even though there is no ארון, Aron, which is quite interesting, as
opposed to now we've been thinking just of a rock, you have
some type of a memory of the כרובים k'ruvim now being carved
into the wall in the back of the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim.
דכתיב Dich-siv ואת כל קירות הבית מסב פתוחי מקלעות V'es kol kiros
habayis misav masa kal'a
and all the walls of the house were some type of a
engraving, braided engraving. Now this is מקדש ראשון, Mikdash Rishon, so at
least that was there also in מקדש שני. Mikdash Sheni. כרובים ותמרות,
K'ruvim v'simoros, cherubs and palm trees ופטורי ציצים u-peturei tzitzim open flowers
וצפה זהב מישר על המחקה v'tzipa zahav miyashar al hamichuka and a
gold fill or you know was filled into the
carvings. So you had carvings in the walls filled with gold. וכתיב
Vich-siv and it says כמער איש ולוית k'ma'ar ish v'livya like the-
which is being read as like the intertwining of a man and
לוית. livyos. מאי כמער איש ולוית? Mai k'ma'ar ish v'livyos? אמר רבה
בר שילא Amar Rabba bar Shila כאיש המעורב בלויה שלו k'ish hime'urab
b'livaya shelo like a man intertwined with his accompaniment, meaning with his
consort. So again the כרובים k'ruvim are not just the כרובים, k'ruvim,
but the כרובים k'ruvim intertwined and that you still had even in
the מקדש שני. Mikdash Sheni. אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish said
Reish Lakish
בשעה שנכנסו נכרים להיכל b'sha'as shenichnesu necharim l'heichal when the non-Jews
entered into the היכל Heichal in the בית שני Bayis Sheni presumably,
ראו כרובים המעורבים זה בזה ra'u k'ruvim ham'uravim zeh b'zeh they saw
the כרובים k'ruvim intertwined. Presumably now we mean the image on the
walls, unless it's referring to בית ראשון, Bayis Rishon, but presumably it's
the image on the walls. הוציאום לשוק, Hotziu'um lashuk, they took them
out out into the marketplace, they completely now they entered into the
most private and they now brought it out into the most public
space. Again, the idea of they saw the כרובים k'ruvim and they
took them out suggests we're talking more about the actual statues of
the כרובים k'ruvim in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but most מפרשים
meforshim understand that this is talking about the בית שני. Bayis Sheni.
So they ripped out, if you would, the
carvings, the wall paneling which had this imagery and they took it
out into the marketplace. ואמרו V'amru and they say ישראל הללו Yisrael
hallalu this Jewish people שברכתם ברכה וקללתם קללה she-birchasam bracha u-kilalasam klala
they're supposed to be so holy, anybody they bless is blessed, like
by Avraham, anybody they curse is cursed, they're so holy. יעסקו בדברים
הללו? Yasku bidvarim hallalu? They should do this type of thing, have
like sexuality in the קודש קדשים? Kodesh Kadashim? מיד הזילום Miyad hizilum
then they denigrated them שנאמר shene'emar כל מכבדיה הזילוהו kol mechabdeha hiziluha
all of those that would honor it, here they honored it, they
said ברכתם ברכה וקללתם קללה birchasam bracha u-kilalasam klala they understood the
importance of ישראל, Yisrael, but now they denigrated them כי ראו ערותה
ki ra'u ervasa they saw its nakedness, its most intimate moment. And
this is very, by the way, quoting the פסוק pasuk here from
איכה Eicha also could suggest the idea of the first בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash which again is much more disturbing and powerful, the actual
statues of the כרובים k'ruvim intertwined on top of the ארון. Aron.
But by the way, what I think powerful about the end of
this is that sex between husband and wife can be the most
powerful and intimate and holy of experiences, but then if it's taken
out and into the marketplace, then it completely denigrates the experience. So
in that place, in that context of the relationship of בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael and God, in that context that actually was the place
where that was holy and that was powerful, but if somebody looks
at it from the outside and they don't have the
context, they see sex maybe always as something pornographic and then they
just went ahead and they made it such by bringing it outside.
But again it's interesting the contrast between bringing it out to the
שוק shuk as opposed to the way the whole thing started which
is all the ways you have to do and all the procedures
you have to do in order to go into the innermost
chambers, that sort being held as the contrast about the power of
that innermost chamber, that coming into the innermost chamber and if you
would the bringing together of humans and God and now the end
about what happened at the חורבן הבית Churban Habayis and the complete
devaluing of it and denigrating of it. Okay, so we'll pick up
tomorrow.